and today uh the we will discuss about
the uh the N to Sr
attention so the actually previously we
already introduced attention as a kind
of a the high level concept concept and
the comparison with the other uh the
method but here we are the the the
discussing the attention based Sr more
details in terms of the architecture and
the actual performance and so
on and the uh first I will explain about
the attention based data which is the
important component based on the enod
deoda
network and the uh initially this uh
method was developed in the the Recon
neur network lstm but now the
Transformer becomes very the dominant uh
in even in the speech area so it's
actually speech area also that Hader
experience of moving to uh the
Transformer so I will explain about it
and then I will also explain about the
recent Advanced architecture uh the
extended from the Transformer uh and the
also the several tips since the uh the
attention based ASL uh is the uh coding
assignment four so I will also try to
put a kind of implementation detail as
much as possible so that you guys can
pass the uh the the coding assignment
for by the several people already
finished a coding assignment
for just want to
note uh so yeah this information also
means that the at least the materials
are good enough
to implement attention based
data
okay okay so uh the uh let's move to the
uh the actual
explanation and many of the first part
may have a overlap with the previous
lectures so please listen to them as a
kind of review of the attention based
as so uh the now that we are moving
toward to the make the the speech
condition to be solved by uh using the
um a single neural network uh models and
so on and this is just a recap uh that I
kind of every time uh they they showing
the this kind of notation that the we
are kind of thinking about the
outputting the token sequence given the
speech feature sequence and then we
always starting from the uh the PW given
or posterior distribution and the
problems is that the T and J are very
different so uh we have to solve this
kind of
problem okay and the PW given o uh again
in the recap uh in the hmm framework
we actually try to decompose the problem
into the three component and further we
introduced the hmm and then this P given
St this part uh has been replaced with
the neural network acoustic model that
was a kind of a previous the two
lectures uh the that they mainly
cover and the uh the this the language
model part we also introduced that this
part can be the represented the neural
network language model the based on the
LM or uh the Transformer language model
and so
on in the attention based ASL actually
we don't need this DEC composition
anymore and what we only use is actually
a probabilistic chain R to factorize
this kind of probability
so from now on uh we focus on this pwj
given uh the history and
observation and this is uh of course uh
just a
distribution but we fortunately we can
actually present this part with a single
neural network compared with other com
combination of the several NE Neal
networks uh in the
before and for this we actually using
the uh encoder decoder
architecture and that is the the the
continuation of the previous explanation
in the language model so this
part if we ignore this observation
condition this is actually purely
language
model so we can actually represent this
part as a neural network language model
which can be lstm or Transformer
whatever
but in the first part of this lecture as
a kind of following the history I will
mostly using the lsdm as an explanation
but later again it can be extended a
Transformer and the this are the
observation how to make it is a kind of
one uh the difficult uh problem uh
because again this is the the different
LS as the uh the the token and we can
not have an alignment
correspondence so this part is are
generally very difficult to the obtain
as a
condition and the first approach uh that
the people started to try is actually
com uh they they convert this
observation as a fix strength
Vector like for example if we use using
the BDM or
whatever and then we can actually get
the fixed Vector in the last part of the
uh
the last part of the the hidden state or
we may actually using the pulling across
the time and so on Anyway by using this
kind of a techniques we could somehow
get the fixed length of the vector here
uh by using the neural
network and then after we have a fixed
LS Vector given this as a condition we
just using the language model and then
we can just generating the token so this
is the the very original idea of try to
uh realize this uh the probability uh in
speech
recognition in this case I will explain
several kind of
notations so first part to get the fixed
uh the vector L Vector this part is kind
of the getting the information of the
input observation and then encode this
information as this fixed Vector so this
are the neural network uh component is
called encoder
Network and after uh we have this kind
of encoder Network we passing the
information and then uh this part is the
large language model or whatever to
generating the token and so on uh this
is uh the given the uh the the encoded
information to decode the the uh the the
the actual the information in our cases
a token sequence so this are part uh of
uh the the dealing with the input
sequence is called encoder Network and
then are there the this part
of dealing with the output of the
sequence it's called the decoda network
and so
on and then this part is connected by
fixed lens so this is a very beginning
of the speech recognition in the uh the
uh the in the uh the try to kind of
model uh this actual
distribution however uh the some of you
uh may know
this part is very
weak regardless of whether this uh the
speech features is very long or very
short we just mapping this information
to the fix length of the
vector if this part has a super large
dimensions it may actually at hold this
kind of
information however by just mapping all
the information to the fix strength is
actually B very rough
approximation so the instead of the just
the converting entire observation speech
feature observation to the fixed length
Vector uh there is a kind of attention
based approaches uh which is actually
try to uh convert this information
depending on the token I will explain
how to do that but before that please
look at this
if we have this kind of information that
is very cool right uh because the
observation speech feature observation
information is actually synchronized
with the uh the output
information so we don't care about the
the different LS right if we have this
kind of information so the uh the idea
of the the encoder decoder architecture
is actually not just are converting the
fix length Vector but the using the
attention mechanism to actually obtain
this uh the the uh the condition
information that is the synchronized
with the output token information so it
can be trival but please remember that
you know this one is you know actually
fix length Vector always you know this
the the last the token uh sorry last
speech feature
time which is actually just a one
instance right so this a fixed vector
and then the original observation o is
are the one to T
variable but uh this one is now
depending on the J which is the same
index as the token so this is the the
goal of our uh the the uh the uh the
formulation
and then uh let's think about what kind
of a condition would be make
sense first uh of course this uh should
have some information to generating the
token WJ right we have to have a
information that the this WJ is the
having a information of HJ and then we
can predict it easily right so these are
one kind of desired property and another
desired property is that alignment
information or
Association this is because this is a
soft alignment but anyway this one is
comes from the entire observation of the
speech features so if we know the kind
of the alignment information between the
this the HJ and entire observation uh
that is reasonable and also explainable
and the third most important part is it
must be
differentiable so that we can use a back
propagation to train entire models so
these are the three Natures properties
are actually statisfied in the attention
mechanism which I already kind of
introduced in the self attention but
today I will explain this the attention
mechanism for the kind of a different
alignment problem
okay so let's uh the first uh the
explain about the uh the uh attention
mechanism again that is already the the
appeared in the self attention context
in the transformer encod in acostic
models but now this attention mechanism
is used to align the different input and
output
problems so first uh the the there is a
kind of little bit confus using no the
notation so but I thought that this is
easier so I just kind of using this
notation but anyway please understand
that h t if the kind of index is T this
comes from the output of the
encoder okay and this is different from
what we want to kind of forget the HJ
here which is depending on the J and
again why I unify this kind of the
notation with h is that this is kind of
both of them
are the uh neural network the the state
vector and easy to actually represent so
that's why kind of we use that the same
notation but please uh they understand
that depending on the uh the index uh
the
subscript uh this is the context vector
or Ang Vector okay
and this one HD is actually the encod
vector not what we want to solve this
one because please look at this one this
part is depending on the input time
while this one is depending on the the
token time right so this is Thea we want
to derive from this one to this
one but to do that first we can just
kind of converting this to the some kind
of neural network values with the
operation this is just to make the kind
of for adjust the dimension or making
this kind of information to be more Rich
based on this kind of the transformation
uh this is called the value which is
also already introduced in the other uh
the self attention
part and then uh similar to the self
attention part what we want to do is
just using the weighted sum okay
just using weighted sum to connect the J
and
T how to do that we just using the
weighted
sum by using this weighted sum we can
actually convert this uh the uh the BT
which is originally from the encoder
representation to the uh the condition
uh of this other probability which is
synchronized with the the token
J and then the uh the question is how to
the obtain this uh the the the weighted
sum and this is actually another way to
use the tension mechanism which is to
convert different lengths of the the
problem to the the the in the the simple
are the
equations and in this case this uh
attention way is actually having the
information of how the speech features
are are assigned with the each of the
kind of state the token the information
so this is for example the if it's
possibly happens is that the first part
of the speech features can have a more
relationship uh with the first part of
the token and the second part of the
token can be kind of related to the the
rest of the middle of the speech feature
set subset and the last part can be also
the represented at the uh the the last
subset of the speech feature so this uh
the AJ attention we is actually also the
having the information of the aligning
the speech feature and so
on however please note that this is the
probabilistic so this is not like a kind
of a the data
istic the alignment so I said that you
know this first part can be aligned to
this one but this is just you know first
part may have a higher priority higher
probabilities than the rest of the
probability and the same for the second
part this can have a higher probability
in the middle part of the subsequence
but not the the the lower probability in
the rest of the the subsequence uh and
and so on so all of this kind of
alignment information is a probabilistic
this is we call it soft alignment and
already introduced in the alignment part
but this is again just a
recap so after uh this uh the alignment
with attention weate was actually
obtained we can also write the the
specific pattern of the the input and
the output
the
relationship and it is a little bit too
small but it is actually J this part
output part we actually add have a
sentence
here and then this T is corres
corresponding to the observation
here and as you see that this are the
attention uh weight is having a high pro
probability in the kind of a diagonal
component uh please note that this kind
of a the dark blue part is probability
is almost zero and the light color means
that the probability is uh the the the
positive and can be very close to one so
if we actually plotting this attention
weight uh we can actually the uh get the
the alignment probability uh in the soft
sense
and this is by the way very good Dearing
method so uh if you guys want to uh uh
check to see your uh attention mechanism
in the encod decod in speech is working
or not I highly recommend you to
actually check this other attention we
and visualize them
cool um the this is the kind of the uh
the the uh typical attention pattern and
as I mentioned uh mathematically there
is no constraint for the alignment but
just you know the speech question it is
actually desired property is the the
monotonic so that it actually turns out
that this is the monotonic
alignment but again I want to mention
that there's no mathematical constant to
make this attention to be a diagonal
so this is actually one of the difficult
part of the the using the attention
based ASR it is the too
flexible and then sometimes actually the
in especially in the beginning in the
beginning of the training uh the the
attention is difficult to uh the train
and then the non monotonic the attention
pattern often happens but later if the
attention
pattern is well trained then the speech
conern cases mostly it becomes monotonic
so please remember this part so that you
guys can actually back what's happening
if we actually implement the the
attention based encod decoda in the
coding assignment
for by the way as I mentioned many times
uh mon monotonic property is only for
the speed spech conition or speech
synthesis we don't need a monotonic the
assign the the the property uh in the
other application like a machine
translation is another big application
of the encoder decoder method and this
is the reordering happens so we don't
need actually the
monotonic the assignment and even for
the speech uh the processing
applications for example the speech
trans ation we also don't need a monic
alignment uh what else uh we our group
is recently actually working quite
actively in the speech summarization
which is given the long speech uh the
recording to get a kind of summary of
what people are kind of speaking in a
few sentence or something like that this
problem is called Speech summarization
and of course we don't need a monotonic
alignment uh or Monon is two are the
strong constraint for the speech
summarization and so
on and again the uh this is actually one
example of the wrong
alignments uh this quite often happens
and the uh the uh you guys may if you
guys Implement coding assignment for and
having this kind of uh the wrong pattern
uh the this is that probably due to some
of the issues in your training but it's
actually the solved by the using the
correct the beam search part so the this
is just a not but this is very typical
the wrong
alignment it's actually uh the
um I I I cannot read by the way this
sentence because I I cannot see the Mand
but I could observe that this
phrases
the repeat it three times
right and this attention pattern is also
three but the same kind of the the word
is repeating three
times uh this is actually quite often
happens in the uh the uh the
uh the when we are the training the uh
the attention based enod de
wrongly and it is kind of little bit
obvious but let's move to the short Qui
question okay so uh the now that I want
to kind of explain about the attention
weight which is uh the uh quite they uh
often discussing the similarity or even
using the same terminology uh with the
information l
uh from now on I will try to kind of
mapping the query key value pit that we
already introduced in our explanation
but more kind of uh the the information
retrial context and how this kind of the
attention weight
observ the derivation based on the key
value key quity value is
reasonable so uh the first uh that the
yeah any of the information Ral system
is fine but uh this is just one uh the
uh the example of the information Ral
system based on the search right uh
first we the follow the
query here in this case is Kano
University and then we actually get a
lot of the other possible the the the
candidate right and this are the the are
corresponding to the key
and then actually the these are
sorted based on the similarity and in
this Cas is top 10 the image that is
close to the the K University is
actually appeared right a very kind of a
familiar concept and this actually
concept is used in the attention uh the
calculation as
well so first uh the the the moving to
this kind of the query and the uh
the uh the uh query and the key uh that
and introducing the
score so we have a query in this case
kind em University and the key is the
kind of medlion or bilion of the
images and the the how to kind of get to
the kind of uh the the more
similar what
the images we actually using the score
function some squ score function and
then at each of the kind of image we
just get some kind of score sorting it
and then getting the most similar one
okay I think this part is not so much
difficult
right okay let's move this one to the
hour the speech uh problem so uh the
query is actually uh represented by the
information of the word token and in our
cases we actually using the hidden State
Vector uh in the kind of a token by the
way unfortunately we cannot use the the
token in the current
one this is because we want to actually
predict this one right we don't know
this answer
yet so the if we know this kind of
answer this one uh we don't have to
actually uh the solve this problem but
our prediction problem is to predict
this kind of a uh the the
token and to do that what information we
feed we feeding the kind of the Hidden
State Vector in the the neural network
language
model until one to T minus one just
before for this one and hope that this
information has a kind of a some
information to predict this one disable
right and then using this one as a query
instead of the token again because we
don't we cannot have this information
yet and then since this one is just a
kind of hidden State Vector designed for
the neural network we just change it to
the linear transformation to some kind
of a other Vector this is more like an
adjustment of the dimensions or kind of
space and then we have a query
information now this one so just you
know WJ is represented by this one and
then key information in our cases
actually this becomes a speech feature
for each time
frame and then again uh we actually uh
changing this uh by using the linear
transform information uh to adjust the
dimensions and also changing the the
space but basically uh this one is the
kind of information of the each other
the speech the feature okay and then
that let's move back to that this one
for each speech feature or in this
example image but anyway in the speech
features we just want to have a score
right
and then we can actually use
whatever in this cases let's using the
inner product if these kind of a
features are both of them are same
Dimension and then we can get just some
scalar value right and making this has a
similarity this is actually the what the
we are actually using for the
information retri so it's same but just
kind of changing the representation of
the query uh the from the uh the uh the
uh hidden State Vector in the language
model part decoder part and then a key
part is comes from the speech
feature and then this it itself may be
already good
information but uh to kind of you making
it more probalistic view let's take the
soft marks and then let's uh making it
the weight
so this becomes the attention weight
which now becomes a kind of pro the
similarity becomes a probability uh but
anyway by using this one like we hit the
some of the the the the uh token and the
corresponding uh image we can actually
the the the through the query comes from
the uh the hidden State uh that has the
information of the WJ
and then we can get the corresponding we
can uh actually hit the
corresponding speech features are based
on the
attention but uh this is not to
know the the designed to be like this uh
by doing this kind of a the function
form and then the finally making this TR
to kind of a making the this one to the
minimize the loss speech loss and so on
and we hope that this one is working
like this this is a kind of attention
mechanism again there is no explicit uh
embedded
relationship between the speech feature
and query this is all kind of a soft
relationship compared with a CTC and so
on so that's why that's kind of a weird
attention pattern unfortunately happens
when uh there a training is especially
not very kind about the uh doing well so
this is the uh the the mostly wise
widely uh used the the uh attention to
kind of a connect the speech uh the
information and the uh output token
information but I just want to recap
that we already introduced attention
right in the self attention and which is
uh also the we can now uh debut this uh
the self attention as kind of a
information to get the kind of a from
the next layer to get the information a
relationship of the previous the context
of the speech features and so on so it's
basically similar but the the self
attention and the cross attention has
some difference of course this is the
cross attention is to connect to the uh
the input and output token while uh
while the the self attention is
connected the the each layer of the
speech features so query is different
query is not from the the output token
uh in the self attention cases quy comes
from the the original the our own kind
of speech feature or the uh the text the
feature and so on and then that making
the attention mechanism and so on so
other than that the all kind of
computation is same actually this is one
of the beauty of the implementation self
attention and cross attention is
basically using the same function form
but just changing for example the query
part from the uh the the the self
attention itself to the the the the the
query obtained from the the target token
the sequence and then without changing
the the function form we can actually
realize these both kind of unique the
operation at the same
time and I mentioned that the uh the the
here uh we actually using the inner
product to get the scar but actually
there are lot of ways to get the scar
this is just one variant and originally
this part was we actually that studied
and one of them is actually using the
neural network to convert this uh the
the uh the two uh the hidden uh the the
state with a nonlinear the function and
then learnable parameter to get the scar
the value and so on there are lot of
actually variant to the make the scar
part uh the uh the to make the kind of
obtain the scar part but anyway the key
idea is just getting the scar and and
inner product is actually quite
sufficient okay so this is the kind of
all component of the attention based
encoder decoder that I are
explained okay not five right
and still four right
okay bit surprised um oh the the encoder
part is uh the speech feature
uh the processing the speech feature so
we could actually using the any of the
operation and actually we could use the
any of the operation I introduced in the
acoustic modeling part I introduced the
feed for neural network comol neural
network uh the the rec neural network
and the the self attention actually we
can use this part with any of them and
attention I mentioned this is the
connection of the decoder part and the
decoder part is uh basically uh the
neural network language model with the
value we came from the
attention so and then this decod part as
I also that covered in the last the the
the lecture which people usually using
the lsdm or the Transformer uh the
decoder and so on and until
2019 actually the speech uh the
recognition uh the attention based ASR
uh is uh the the actively studied based
on the rec
network but uh uh in the the the 20
around
2019 actually people started to move to
the uh the Transformer and which is a
little bit kind of later than the
already NLP people working on the
Transformer but anyway two years later
uh the speech people also started to use
the
Transformer and now I move to the
explanation about
Transformer uh any questions so
far okay after that mostly neural
network engineering so I just kind of
exem about you know the combin this one
combine this one so it's not so much
difficult
concept um the
uh since
2019 uh the the speech uh the people
actually started to use the the
Transformer and the uh the the the
that's the post the the encoder uh and
the decoder and I will explain a bit
more about the details about the
Transformer by the way the uh this is
actually one of the uh the uh the the
contribution in the ESP net project this
uh the second paper is showing that the
uh entire
15 the the ASR Bas Baseline benchmarks
and the Transformer is better than the
the lsdm after this paper was published
uh many kind of researchers actually
moving from the uh the rec Network to uh
the the Transformer so I still remember
uh these kind of
activities and this paper is actually
one of the most cited paper in asru in
this kind of five
years okay so again this part is more
for the uh just kind of introducing the
several layers so I will mostly skip or
ask you guys to check some details about
the other other neuron network uh the
papers and so on but first part is
positional and very
actually the the Transformer the
operation is basically the O agnostic
it's actually cannot really kind of
understand the the order information and
sometime reorder can be happened inside
the neural network so to prevent the the
reordering positional embedding is
actually used to avoid uh mitigate the
issue of the O diagnostic operation in
the the the Transformer this is is
actually one uh
component important in the
Transformer and the second part is the
uh the the one that we already discussed
MTI head
extension uh this is the self attension
since it is the inside encoder but
anyway uh the instead of using just a
single
attention uh we usually using the
multiple attentions
four or eight or depending on the kind
of the model size architecture and so
on and after we have a this kind of
parallel uh
attention uh we actually just
concatenate and then making a big the
vector and then passing it to the later
stage and this concatenation and Par the
the Computing the attention is again it
can be well parallelized uh so that it
is the having information of modeling
various speeech Dynamics but also
satisfying the polarization of the
information and this is actually example
of the the March head
attention and this is again self
attention so it's not cross attention
it's not like you know input output it's
just a self attention but uh uh this is
actually one answer for the your
question
so this one is diagonal it's self
tension mostly should be diagonal to
other get the information because you
know the most relevant information comes
from the their own right but actually
interestingly there are several other
different patterns in
general uh this means that the like for
example this one is actually try to
capture the
neighboring information very
interesting and this one is a little bit
difficult to interpret uh one part
probably this actually capture the
global information but the other part
maybe it's just a
noise uh the the for example even
removing some of them it's still working
well so there is actually one of the the
important compression technique in
speech recogition is try to removing
this kind of a non diagonal element
actually doesn't the degrad performance
so much so this means that the uh the
diagonal pattern is the most important
but sometimes some people also again are
explain that this can capture the global
information in our case like a speaker
or noise or something like that uh but I
don't have so much kind of clear
evidence about it especially everything
I'm very sure that some of them are just
Noise Okay after we extend the the the
March the head
attention and then after that we
actually also have a additional feed
forward the neural
network and then they getting the kind
of output and so on and the layer Norm
is sometimes in between the the
operation which is actually normalizing
the feature that makes the kind of
convergence are quite other
reasonable and the another important
operation which was the originally well
kind of developed in the image computer
vision is that residual
connection uh that means that it's
actually copying the input feature and
uh the neural network is only adjusting
the residual
component that is again you know only
residual component so uh that you could
imagine that P can be easier than the
predict everything right and actually
this easier me that has the two meaning
it's actually yes the easy to uh the
estimate the parameters and also by uh
doing this kind of a connection back
propagation can have a short shortcut
here so that the optimization also
becomes very stable based on this
residual connection and this regid
connection is also used in the
Transformer encoder
and then now I explained about the uh
the I just explained about the uh the
encoder and now I move to decoder but
actually decoder doesn't have so much
changes one part of the change is that
front end
part when I explained about the uh the
acoustic modeling I already mentioned
that always we have a uh the comosition
of your network based uh down sampling
in the
input speech
features but uh of course we don't need
this kind of operation in the decoder
which is the more like language model
part right instead we just having a
token embedding it's kind of converting
the the word to the the linear space
that we discussed in the uh the neural
network language model and so on and
then uh it's also has a uh the the since
this is the neural network language
model so this is uh the caal the the
decoder the ca self attention instead of
the the normal self attention so on but
in addition to this
component uh the most important part is
that the the uh the attention the
computation uh for the the input part
this actually usually inserted
here and then uh the by doing that we
actually
condition this uh the the uh the decoder
uh based neural network language model
uh with the input the information
vention mechanism so basically uh the uh
this is the kind of the difference but
except for that the encoder and decoder
is actually very similar architecture uh
that is also very kind of a cool part of
the Transformer basically we don't have
to change so much about the function
form we just changing some kind of input
or we just kind of inserting the cross
attention and then we can actually make
a Transformer and cod decoder and again
this kind of our high level design part
is one of the homework in the coding
assignment
for and since this is the the coding
assignment so I will also present
several kind of the tips when you kind
of implementing it yes okay
um so the uh now I move to the uh
tips and the uh first uh the part uh of
the the important uh the the information
in the Transformer is that the uh
generally uh the running rate is little
bit tricky so running rate is actually
uh the the behaving like this this is
intentionally we make this kind of
function for the running R this means
that the first few EPO by the way the
where we kind of making a peak is the
one of the hyper
parameter uh this are the region called
warm up so we starting from the small
running rate and gradually increasing it
so that it's kind of the neural network
as kind of it is trained it's may find a
kind of better Solutions in the
beginning and then we actually making
this kind of a larning the rate Behavior
but later if the running rate is too
large it actually cannot find the better
solution uh to do that we actually are
try to gradually decreasing the running
rate so this the running rate the
scheduling is quite common uh in the uh
the the trans
based approaches it can be applied to
many of them but that after the
Transformer this the the optimization
techniques becomes very
popular and then there are two
parameters one is when we kind of a set
a peak and the other is the absolute
value so these are the two hyper
parameter is actually
tuning and the this uh learning rate
tuning is necessary unfortunately
necessary
uh there is no other the uh the best
parameter that will be working on
everything so please uh always first
tuning the the running rate and then the
find the some kind of optimum uh the
solutions so it's quite often happen
that the Transformer doesn't actually
converge at all or train at all or over
trining under tring and just at tuning
the learning rate can generally solve
this issue again uh learning rate tuning
is
necessary very few cases I didn't tune
but most cases I actually Cho the
learning rate otherwise it doesn't
actually showing the full benefit of uh
the
architecture and another important part
is the
aaging actually instead of using the
single model optimized in the uh the
neural network we generally uh aaging
the the models in a 10 box or something
like
that
even is uh the model aaging the prepared
in the coding assignment
for no okay so this part can be actually
one point that may improve the
performance uh it's the my experience
always relatively 10% uh the the um uh
the the the Improvement we can get if we
kind of modeling the parameters and so
on this comes from the fact that the
neural network is again kind of every
kind of the the uh the training it's
actually slightly fluctuating and some
cases it can be actually overly trained
but if we kind of averaging across the
kind of previous uh data models and then
this kind of a fluctuation issu is are
the mitigated so model averaging is also
Al quite important
technique and the other important part
is batch size batch size is very
important well I already discussed in
the batch size but the larger batch size
is actually important for the
Transformer however B sides is a
limitation if we don't have enough GPU
memory we cannot actually increase the
GPU size sorry but size anymore right
and then there is a technique called the
gradient accumulation which is actually
the Bally increasing the B size this by
the way doesn't kind of improve the
training speed but just virtually
increase the bch size so for example
instead of uh the taking the uh the
gradient and then updating the
parameter we take for example two uh the
the first we kind of Performing the
gradient and then saving the
miniat doesn't upgrate the parameter
okay doesn't up moving to the next uh
miniat getting the uh the the
gradient and the gradient has addien so
we can actually adding them accumulating
it this corresponding to actually the
the the working on the two uh minib
sides
at one kind of
gradient one kind of parameter
optimization right so this actually
virally increasing the batch
size so this doesn't kind of again the
uh the change the kind of training speed
and so it can be actually slower because
up number of update becomes smaller
however transform actually want to have
a large but size to make it are the uh
stably working
so in these cases uh this uh gradient
accumulation is very
important I I know that there is a very
interesting discussions actually the
after Google uh the the pre uh the
propos Transformer the open source the
project tries to follow Transformer but
they couldn't actually reproduce the the
Google result and they actually
contacted the Google people what's the
difference
and found that the B size is the most
diff the important part however Google
has a TPU and we don't have a the the we
couldn't use TPU at that time and we
couldn't actually make the the same size
the same minat sit as Google did and
then people actually using this other
the gradient accumulation techniques and
the Transformer was finally reproduced
other other than Google team so anyway
this gradient accumulation is very
important and many of the modern tool is
actually having this
implementation and the last part is
check the
ls this is also very typically
happens so as I as you remember
Transformer has basically are the the
square the lenss of the the square of
the lenss is uh the the computational
cost so it can be input it can be input
and output this is actually Closs
attention part and it can be the the
output part and we actually required a
lot of GPU memories and very typical
questions which you know we want to
avoid to you know answer the typical
questions in the P so I want to mention
many people just you know deporting that
the my the data having the GPU memory
issue
is and there might be an issue comes
from the you know your network might be
very large but most of the cases it
actually comes from here and most of the
cases you guys including a very long
sequence it can be input or
output but in this cases of course this
memory becomes kind of too large and the
training is stopped right and then easy
solution is just removing this kind of
long sentences
this is very kind of a powerful
technique so please remember that uh
without that you guys actually may have
some kind of issues uh to the TR the
Transformer and so
on okay so that's the uh the uh the the
tips and I hope you guys can actually
make the coding assignment for works at
least coding assignment for again you
don't need a multiple
gpus and then now I kind of explain
about the impact of the Transformer this
is actually the result that I extracted
from our papers which actually gave the
big impact of how Transformer is
important in speech so before that
actually there were big discussion
whether Transformer is really kind of
important for speech or not but after
our papers we actually showing that one
two three four five six seven eight
15 tasks and let's compare it with the
RNN versus
Transformer and the almost all the kind
of our
tasks uh
the the the transforma is actually
better than recur NE
Network so with this result actually
again the many people started to use the
transformer in speech recognition now it
becomes very kind of popular standard so
actually many people started to forget
this kind of work since you know the
people knew that now the Transformer is
very kind of a powerful but before that
actually around 2000 everyone was
actually the the the excited about our
result of this kind of very good
performance in the
Transformer and this is actually uh one
of the uh the the work that we have done
and at that time the the all kind of
method are based on the RNN
and then the Google people actually
having a very good performance by using
the technique called spec augment but
spec augment and Recon Network and this
is as you see big jump from the the
previous kind of best result right and
everyone thought that you know it is
very difficult to compete with uh the
Google but actually uh by using the the
espet the Transformer we can actually uh
reading uh their performance by the way
we also using a spec orent so we use a
spec orent and the Transformer and then
the finally getting the kind of a result
that Google guys are doing with the uh
the RN based approaches so it's not a
very fair comparison but anyway with
their kind of a big resources and a lot
of try outs they actually get quite
impressive result but we can actually
get the kind of a good result by using
the the good the method good tools good
weapon uh in this case is Transformer
and I kind of using this kind of
figure just I open use this one by the
way which one is
Google this part right the Google Amazon
Facebook Apple Microsoft the uh this
giant are actually quite good but by
using the ESP net and by using the
Transformer that we can somehow compete
with
them however uh they actually you know
still very good they actually proposed
the new
method named cona this is actually the
variant of the attention the Transformer
based approach is augmented by the
compolation neural network so which I
will explain uh in Wednesday okay uh
that's it thank you